Guide to the Walter Metzger American Association of University Professors Records of Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1888-2009 MS2369
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Correspondence, 1914-2006; Series 5
  - December 7, 1915 to January 17, 1916, 1915-1916; Series 5 (Box 84, Folder 8)
  - Committee A Procedures- 1916 and Subsequent, 1926-1961; Series 5 (Box 84, Folder 9)
    Folder contains materials associated with Seligman correspondence files.
  - Seligman Microfilm, 1916-1922; Series 5 (Box 84, Folder 10)
  - Alabama Case, 1916-1917; Series 5 (Box 84, Folder 11)
  - April 1, 1916 to May 17, 1916, Series 5 (Box 84, Folder 12)
  - Iowa Case, 1916; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - May 18, 1916 to May 31, 1916, Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - June 1, 1916 to June 30, 1916, Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - July 1, 1916 to October 8, 1916, Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 4)
  - Stanford Case, 1916-1917; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 5)
  - October 9, 1916 to November 30, 1916, Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 6)
  - Texas Case (1 of 2), 1916-1917; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 7)
  - Texas Case (2 of 2), 1916-1917; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 8)
  - December 1, 1916 to January 31, 1917, 1916-1917; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 9)
  - February 1, 1917 to March 31, 1917, Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 10)
  - Connecticut Case (1 of 2), 1917; Series 5 (Box 85, Folder 11)
  - Connecticut Case (2 of 2), 1911-1916; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 1)
  - Connecticut Case (3 of 4), 1917; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Connecticut Case (4 of 4), 1917; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - April 1, 1917 to April 30, 1917, Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 4)
  - May 1, 1917 to May 31, 1917, Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 5)
  - June 1, 1917 to June 30, 1917, Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 6)
  - Colorado Collage Case: Parsons, 1917; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 7)
  - July 1, 1917 to July 31, 1917, Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 8)
  - August 1, 1917 to November 12, 1917, Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 9)
  - Columbia University- New York (1 of 2), 1936-1945; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University- New York (2 of 2), 1930-1935; Series 5 (Box 86, Folder 11)
  - Maryland- Schwartz, 1952-1953; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 1)
  - Morgan State- Diggs, 1950-1951; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 2)
  - Loyola- Young, 1954; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 3)
  - Maryland State- George, 1954; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 4)
  - Letter to Bierstedt, December 10, 1971; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 5)
  - Papers on Academic Economy, 1984; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 6)
  - Readings for Bancroft Prize, 1978-1979; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 7)
  - Letter on My Remarks: "Vexation", May 31, 1980; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 8)
  - Letter on Sheila Slaughter, October 14, 1988; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 9)
  - GMAC: Report on Wechsler- Schlossman Proposal, 1987; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 10)
  - Letter: AAA Complaint, 1988; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 11)
  - Letter on Tsongas- Rudman, May 14, 1996; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 12)
  - Letter to Judy Thomson on Jordan Kurland, December 10, 1997; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 13)
  - RAPP- Coudert, 1981; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 14)
  - Letter: Attack on Whiche, 1972; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 15)
  - Comments- Himstead- Fuchs, 1987; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 16)
  - New York State Council for Humanities- Letter, 1984-1985; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 17)
  - Letter to Dean Frank Wolf, 1991; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 18)
  - Letters: Miscellaneous, 1992-2007; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 19)
  - To Bob and Adele Clark, December 30, 2006; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 20)
  - Remembrance of Bentley Glass, January 27, 2005; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 21)
  - Remembrance of Ralph Brown, 1998; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 22)
  - Letters on Institutional Mergers, 1979-1982; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1915- 1916; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 24)
  - Federal and Local Tax- File # 1 (1 of 2), 1943-1946; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 25)
  - Federal and Local Tax- File # 1 (1 of 2), 1934-1943; Series 5 (Box 87, Folder 26)
  - Committee A Correspondence, 1937-1939; Series 5 (Box 89, Folder 1)
  - Committee A Correspondence, 1934-1937; Series 5 (Box 89, Folder 2)
  - Committee A Correspondence, 1927-1933; Series 5 (Box 89, Folder 3)
  - Committee A Correspondence, 1926-1931; Series 5 (Box 89, Folder 4)
  - "Re-Placement" Service, 1938-1939; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 1)
  - Principles, Procedures, etc., 1926-1938; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 2)
  - Hearst Anti- Radical, 1926-1938; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Financial Exigency, Tenure In, 1945; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 4)
  - Eligible List, 1933-1945; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 5)
  - Discrimination, 1945; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 6)
  - Council and Chapter Letters, 1941-1951; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 7)
  - Harvard Chapter, 1947-1950; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 8)
  - Federal and Local Taxation- File 2, 1947-1952; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 9)
  - My Comments: "A" Cases (1 of 2), 1963-1998; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 10)
  - My Comments: "A" Cases (2 of 2), 1967-1994; Series 5 (Box 90, Folder 11)
- Card Catalogues, 1820-1970; Series 6
  This series contains catalogue cards created by Walter Metzger, which compiles notes of topics that can be found in within previous series. Each box contains a narrowed listing of catalogued topics titled by the donor. These boxes are dated between 1820-1970.
  This series is arranged by subject.
  - History of AAUP: Himstead and Fuchs and 1915- Himstead, 1933-1958; Series 6 (Box 91)
    History of AAUP Himstead and Fuchs includes: Himstead Pre GS, Himstead Election, Himstead and Cases 1936-1948, Himstead's GS-ship 1936-1948, Character- General, Interviews, Committee O, Himstead 1949-1955, Search for GS, Communist Policy 1947-1956, 1956 Report- Cases, 1956 Report, Fuchs, 1958
    History of AAUP 1915- Himstead includes: History- Epochs, Depression Problems, War Problems, Democratizing Problems 1933-1935, Democratization 1936-1939, Complainants, Personality- Complainant, AAUP Relation To, Complainant Attitude Towards
  - History of AAUP: 1915- Himstead and Founding of AAUP, and World War I, undated; Series 6 (Box 92)
    History of AAUP 1915- Himstead includes: Administrations, Institutions, Trustees, Deans and Department Heads, Presidents, AAUP Relations, Other Committees, Professional Ethics, Educational Quality, Pensions, Faculty Administrators, Appointment Service, Lobbying, Economic Status, Bulletin, External Relations, A.A.C, A.F.T., Accrediting Agencies, NEA and Secondary Schools, General, Leaders, Maguire, Cook
    Founding of AAUP includes: Founding, Lovejoy, Tyler, Other Early Leaders, Organization, Chapters, Membership- Early, Membership Changes
    World War I includes: World War One (General)
  - World War I and the History of Tenure, 1820-1940; Series 6 (Box 93)
    World War I includes: Pacifism, German-Americans, Cattell Case, W.W.I. Cases, Willis Rudy, 1918
    History of Tenure includes: Tenure- Colonial To 1913, Harvard, William and Mary, Tenure Systems 1820-1915, Presidential Response, Civil Service, School Teachers, The Ministry, Tenure-Contemporary, History of Tenure 1913-1940, Collective Bargaining, Legal Development, Financial Exigency, Tenure Abroad, 1915 Statement, 1914, 1915, 1940 Statement, What is 1940 Statement, Response for Revision
  - History of Tenure, 1915, 1925, and 1940 Statements, and Committee A Procedure and Reports- Historical, 1956-1970; Series 6 (Box 94)
    History of Tenure, 1915, 1925, and 1940 Statements includes: History of Negotiations, Endorsements, Effects of 1940 Statement, Agreement in Writing, Ground for Dismissal, Freedom of Teaching, Freedom of Research, Extramural Freedom, Religious Exemption, Preamble, Academic Freedom- Who?, Termination and Non-Tenure, Probationary Period, Temporary or Part-time, 1970 Interpretations, Financial Exigency, Non-Retroactive Clause, 1956
    Committee A Procedure and Reports includes: Committee A, Selection, Committee A- Early, Cases- Statistics, Committee A- Chairman, Internal Function A, Regional Division A, Washington Office A, Local Chapters A, Due Process, Waver, Discrimination, Resignation, Retirement, Anti- AAUP Reprisal, Investigating Cases, Investigators, Witnesses, Mediations, Reports, Report- Scope, Report- Type
  - Committee A Procedure and Reports and Academic Freedom in Law and in U.S. Profession, 1865-1920; Series 6 (Box 95)
    Committee A Procedure and Reports includes: Report- Quality, Reports- Judgements, Report- Suppression, Report- Revision, Report- Rejoinder, Report- Review, Report- Libel, Cases, Cases- Speed, Cases- Censure, Cases- Redress, Prevention- Reform, Mediation, Arbitration, Boycotts, Role in Society
    Academic Freedom in Law and in U.S. Profession includes: 2 Meanings of Academic Freedom, 1st Amendment History, Classroom Freedom, Extramural Freedom, Employee Gripe, Student Freedom, School Teachers, Search Freedom, Due Process, Discrimination, Religious Colleges, Judicial Analysis, Contracts, Financial Exigency, Judicial Remedies, Tenure and Academic Freedom, Confidentiality and Disclosure, Academics and the Law, Academic Freedom 1865-1915, Academic Freedom 1865-1920, Ross Case, 1900-1913
  - Academic Freedom in Law and in U.S. Profession and British Universities, 1916-1917; Series 6 (Box 96)
    Academic Freedom in Law and in U.S. Profession includes: AAUP First Five, Utah, Montana, Colorado, Pennsylvania, Wesleyan, 1916-1917, Institutional Neutrality, Endowed Chairs, Student Freedom, Communism, Scientific Freedom
    British Universities includes: For Annon Interview, Britain, Academic Profession, Britain- History of Universities, Britain- Historyof Academic Profession, Britain- Governance, Britiain- Funding of University Students, Halsey- Trow, Ideals and Values, Access, Teaching and Research, Public Sector, Conditions of Work, Britain- Expansion
  - British Universities and Religion in Academe, undated; Series 6 (Box 97)
    British Universities includes: Britain- Thatcher Government, Britain- Academic Freedom, A.U.T Council, Education Reform Act
    Religion in Academe includes: Religiousness- Secularization, General, Seminarianism, Clericality, Cloistered. Denominational Control, Religion and Science, Sectarianism, Religious Tests, Secularization
  - Economy and Governance- Past and Present, 1800-1913; Series 6 (Box 98)
    Box includes: Study of Academic Economy, Academic Economy 1800-1860, Enrollment, Tuition Costs, Gifts- Endowments, State Subsidy, Faculty Salaries, Size of Faculty, Academic Economy 1865-1900, Statistics, Expansion, Expansion- International, Notes- "Growing, Growing, Gone", Academic Economy- Current, Faculty Jobs, Institutional Budgets, Federal Aid, Faculty Income, Market Projections, Current Faculty, Gender, Racial Background, Age, Class Background, Religious Background, Training, Workloads, Benefits, Retirement, Part-time Faculty, Quality Today, Teaching vs. Research, Collective Bargaining, Academic Governance History- MED- 1913, Rashdall- Medieval, Reformation- Oxbridge, Reformation- Continent, Colonial
  - Economy and Governance- Past and Present and Diversification Specialization, 1800-1900, 1913; Series 6 (Box 99)
    Economy and Governance includes: Corporations- Dartmouth College, Governance Pre-Civil War, Beach 19th Century, Private and Public Origins Today, Self- Government 1913, Germany Self-Governing Academic Freedom, Presidential Power, Shared Authority 1913, Commercialization 1913, Efficiency Cult- Taylorism, Governance- History After Cattell, Delocalization, Departments, Peer Review, Trustees
    Diversification and Specialization includes: Historiography- Antebellum College, Academizing Knowledge, Tests of Admission, Sponsorship, Formation of Disciplines, Quantum Theory, Structural Aspects, Fundamentailty, Marginal Diversification, Curriculum Pre- Civil War, Antebellum Reform, Natural Sciences, Social Sciences
  - Diversification Specialization, 1800-1900 and Academic Profession, 1828-1900; Series 6 (Box 100)
    Diversification Specialization includes: Professional Schools, Languages, Engineering, Yale Report 1828, Curriculum Post-Civil War, Traditional Colleges, Natural Sciences, Social Sciences, Theological Seminaries, Research- Graduate Schools, Specializations
    Academic Profession includes: Academic Profession- General, Historians on Academic Professions, Sociologists on Academic Professions, Ethics, Professional Changes, Study Abroad, Recruitment, School Teaching, Academic Teaching, Faculty Size, Academic Professionalism 1965-1900, Intellectuals, Development of Learned Professions, Social Characterisics, Training in Graduate Schools, Evaluation and Promotion, Income, Status- Public, Appointments, Quality, Rise of Professional Consciousness
  - Academic Profession and Untitled Cards, 1925; Series 6 (Box 101)
    Academic Profession includes: Professionalism, Definition, Social Background, Training, Clientele, Organizations, Ethics, Compensation, Licensure, Anti-Professionalism, Knowledge, Community, Bureaucracy, "Professional Men"Geison- General, Larson, Haber, Carr-Saunders, Starr, Abbott, Friedson, Parsons, Kimball, Demnominations, Asymetrical Relations
    Untitled Card include: 1925, 1925- History, Notice, Termination- Tenure, Academic Due Process, Reader-England
  - Untitled Cards, 1919-1958; Series 6 (Box 102)
    Box includes: Tenure Debate, 1919, 1920-1924, 1925-1929, 1930-1931, 1932-1934, 1935-1936, 1937-1940, 1941-1949, 1956-1958, 1950-1954, 1955-present